Then Ben turned up and blew the mixer up, I was playing after him, so he blew the headphone
jack up so I had to DJ for an hour on vinyl with no headphones, so I didn't care because
I got to meet Ben and it was, you know, we'd felt that like oh my god, we've not just
put a party on with friends, we've put a party on and we've booked, you know,
the guy at the time, because obviously...
Welcome to the very first episode of the Valkyrie Podcast.
I'm your host, Tom aka Tangents from Valkyrie.
The aim with these podcasts is to create a place for long-form interesting conversations
with our artists and people that we care about and I'm really excited to kick things
off today with the mighty Killbox aka EdRussianAudio.
Now at Valkyrie, we're celebrating Killbox's comeback EP, which has just come out as
the debut release on our label, Killer of Killers, so I encourage you to all
check that out, it's a wicked EP, it's amazing, go listen to it.
And today, we're not just going to get into aspects of the EP, but we're going to go
way deeper into their artist journey, origins of the scene, changing face of the scene,
technology, aliens, there's all sorts of stuff in here, so yeah, I really enjoyed
having this conversation with the Killbox guys, so I hope you enjoy it too.
So to kick things off, we're going to dive straight into the middle of the conversation
where we're discussing the prospect of EdRush getting on the mic during shows.
I did it on the Australian tour, I did it in November, there was a couple of daytime raves
and Wilkinson was on before me and he was like, every couple of tunes he was going for it
and I felt like that was adding on to the energy, so I felt like it was necessary
and I wasn't too smashed, I could string a sentence together still, so I'm like,
let's have a little go, so that wasn't too bad.
Just here and there randomly, like Japan, I've done it a couple of times and things like that.
I think there's a time and a place, there's a time where it's essential
and you've really just got to dig deep and just do it, even though it's uncomfortable, it's horrible.
You hopped on the mic for a little speech at the end of Neuroheads last year
and that felt right.
Yeah, exactly, it's organic and it feels like it's going to add on in a good way.
It felt very community vibe there, so it felt like the right thing to do.
Do you reckon different audiences expect different things with the mics and stuff?
I don't know, it seems like the American audiences, I've been hearing things
with the great find that certain DJs are being encouraged to do this.
I think in the States especially, if there's no MC, I think a lot of the ravers
and the festival crowd kind of expect a bit of communication, it's nice to hear a human voice.
You know what, that's interesting, I hadn't thought about it that way actually
because I guess often times we kind of take the MC host duties for granted sometimes.
Yes, yeah you do.
And you know what, I never thought about it that way, not having a host for an EDM artist or something.
And it can become quite stilted, can't it? You go on.
Well I mean, it was like the fundamental parts of Jungle and Drummer Base were to have,
you had a host, you had an MC, when I first got into it, that was part of it.
It was only when you started really going to sort of Europe,
where they didn't perhaps have that connection with Darb and Reggae and they were doing Drummer Base,
they would find it like, why have you got someone talking, it's annoying, it's detracting from the tracks.
So yeah, I think that influence is better now in Europe where they kind of understand
that Drummer Base has an MC and you know, they're a little bit,
but you still go to places don't you, where they're just, they're not interested,
they just want to hear you play music, which is great, because that's what I'm there to do.
So I can quite easily not talk for two hours and just play tunes.
Yeah, for sure. But like, it's just interesting to see the differences, isn't it?
Yeah, and the amount of comments you see online of like, I wish there was no MC on this set.
But it's different across the world.
You might get people in certain parts of the world saying that and other people enjoy it and think it adds on in a positive way.
But it definitely comes from like Sound Clash culture.
Yeah.
From sort of, you know, hollering, shouting for the rewind and stuff like that.
That's kind of the roots of it all.
Yeah.
And some parts of the world didn't really have that as a part of growing up for them.
Whereas we did, it's part of British culture.
Yeah, that's one of the things I love about this scene.
Like everyone has their own route in and like the Valkyrie crew are quite an international crew,
you know, like Annie's come from Singapore, from the Asian side of things.
I learned from Ukraine, like it's all different.
Everyone's got their own kind of story and stuff that I might kind of expect or take for granted growing up in the UK,
like UK things, like they've had different experiences and they see it with new eyes.
I think that's so interesting.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
Talking about kind of like the scene stuff, one of the things I wanted to talk to you guys about,
like you connected from like the sort of free party scene, right?
Like back in the day, like tell us a little bit about that, because that's a whole chapter that like my generation and others,
we weren't able to participate in that.
Yeah.
I think especially as like nostalgia is always super powerful, you see it in the branding,
you see it like the traces of it in the culture.
But like was one like a spiral tribe?
Yeah, it's kind of before it was hit the clubs, before it was commercial in any way.
Yeah.
Before you found it on in any kind of major clubs in any city, there was a big movement within the music
through pirate radio stations and stuff like that.
I worked on three or four pirate radio stations.
What were you doing there?
DJing, Don FM, Flex FM.
And we would find someone would allow us to use their apartment or their flat for the day.
And you'd set the rig up on that is normally on a council estate on a high rise.
So you could put the aerial right up to reach maximum.
Like Corrupt FM.
Exactly.
Exactly that.
It was basically that.
And you just move from flat to flat.
And if you got caught, they'd confiscate all the gear.
You'd lose all your tunes, all your dub plates, which was terrifying,
because I'd go there with like a grand's worth of dub plates.
And if they were gone, that was it.
Like no.
Yeah, you can't just whack out another USB and you're good to go.
Yeah, exactly.
And the pirate radio stations would kind of work in conjunction with a lot of the spiral tribe guys as far as sharing information.
So it'd be like the parties in Oxford.
We don't quite know where it is yet.
But we're meeting at this petrol station at 11 p.m.
on junction blah, blah of the M25.
That kind of information like arms race, just keeping one step ahead of all the authorities or people you don't want to show up.
200 cars would show up at this petrol station.
It would be like Chinese whispers like, oh, it's at so-and-so, it's at so-and-so.
And then this big convoy would drive off to this poor farmer's field.
They just got jacked for the night.
See, Ben lived in London, so he sort of had access to those sort of parties where I lived sort of out in the countryside and out on a stick.
So, yeah, I would just I wouldn't be able to travel to pirate to do pirate radio station,
but I would have a hanger outside the window trying to pick up, you know, reception and record tapes of it.
And then, yeah, like my way in was doing free parties with with friends, just setting up in disused buildings,
sitting a rig up and just hoping the police don't turn up.
Many times the police did turn up and shut everything down.
But, yeah, I think that's that energy that kind of do it yourself.
Energy has always been in dance music and EDM and especially from the UK.
So, yeah, I think we both just we both came in that way, but just different angles.
Again, we're talking about angles of things.
Yeah, yeah, I definitely see that like creativity, ingenuity and like that rebelliousness.
Like that is right in the DNA of this music.
It's like punk, isn't it?
Yeah, it's that it's that rebellion.
We go against the system.
We do what we want when we want to do mentality.
And we just instead of being like with a band, it's now with, you know, with big sound systems and decks and records and stuff.
So, yeah.
And you feel like you're part of really something special because it's always like a small community that start off with those movements.
Yeah. And you feel like you're part of this kind of exclusive thing and that not most people don't know about it.
And that's that's really cool because you get that sense of community and, like, you know, connection with other people with similar interests and stuff.
Yeah. And I heard someone else talk about it, like another DJ in the scene talk about it.
Like it was like a secret, like exclusive club, but the only requirement is like you just have to show up and get involved.
Yeah. Once you step through that door, like, yeah, you're in your world.
We were talking about yesterday in another interview about Valkyrie and what you guys are trying to do with this community.
And it really feels that you're bringing that sense of community back or trying to that.
I feel that we've kind of lost, really, where everything's a bit faceless and, you know, impersonal and stuff.
It feels like you're trying to bring that back, which is which is a lovely thing, because it's how I it was one of the most it was one of the attractive parts of
drum and bass or electronic music at that point was that sense of community wasn't just I love the music and what what it said to me and how it touched my soul.
It was also that feeling of like I'm with this with brothers and sisters who feel exactly the same as well as I do.
And it's feel as strongly as I do about this thing.
So we're all like minded people. So you just naturally feel comfortable.
Any ideas that you had didn't feel silly to say because everyone would get where you're coming from.
Do you know what I mean? 100 percent like that.
That resonates super strongly with me because my experience moving to London like on my own and then I started going out to events on my own because my friends quickly,
like they ran out of steam and didn't have the same level of obsession for going to everything that I could.
You know, that was like now that I had this new world that was open to me.
And you just naturally like you form these connections with people.
And it's been interesting for me to see, like some of my peers, like I'm I'm in my early 30s now.
Some of them feel a bit isolated in London sometimes.
You know, like it can be hard for them to meet new people outside work.
I feel very blessed to have had this thing in my life that like has connected me with so many amazing people like, you know, yourselves.
And friends that you'll have, regardless of what how your journey is within the music, if it stops or it falters in any way,
connections that you'll have that last beyond that for the rest of your life.
Now, you know, people, you know, I know Ben because of them, not because of the music, but because we're friends.
Do you know what I mean? You gain so much from it.
So, yeah, I'm glad you brought a community like that's something that is so important to us.
We were talking about yesterday.
It's one. It's one of the reasons we're really attracted to actually working with you guys was the fact that you were so heavily prioritizing
the idea of community and how when we were getting into the scene, that was everything like it was all like, yeah,
you could recognize another raver from your outfit.
Yeah, it was oversized clothing and bucket hats and like, you know, whistles and stuff and glow sticks.
It's like, oh, there's there's another raver.
And you instantly felt that rapport and that connection.
That's a little bit lost these days because I feel like everything's kind of generic and kind of washed out a little bit.
And I think with social media and stuff, although obviously it connects everyone,
it's also isolating in a way because people don't go out as much because they're getting dopamine hits and just sitting on their own in their bedroom.
So in a way, we're kind of losing, although we're more connected,
there's a loss of community with all this tech and social media.
And I think what you guys are doing with your WhatsApp group and all that kind of stuff is rejuvenating that idea and bringing everyone back together in a healthy way
and interacting with everyone.
And when they come out to the nights, they'll recognize each other.
Oh, I'm so and so from chat.
Oh, you're blah, blah, blah.
And then they had some virus at the weekend.
And they put faces to the names that they've been talking to for the last month or two months, whatever it might be.
And I think that's really powerful and something that we both thought was really cool.
Yeah, I'm super glad to hear that.
Like, you know, we're figuring it out.
You know, like you guys, I think you both talked about, I guess, in this increasingly digital world.
Like you can lose a bit of that connection and that warmth.
And I don't know, like not everything's going to work, but we want to try because we felt like what it's done for us.
And I still see people I meet in the scene who like those moments can still exist.
But I feel they just may be a bit rarer, you know, and like they're even more special because of it.
Like I've got a friend I met, like through hospital events, I think.
And he met his his like raving crew.
He was at a trade show for work and he had like a ram lanyard or something that he had put his pass in.
And the person that was giving him a tour just like locked onto it.
Yeah, you know, like these little moments, they can still exist.
But it feels like they can be a bit harder to find sometimes.
You know, it's tribalistic coming together with a group of people listening to the same music.
It's it's very tribal.
And we're coming together as a as just one people under one roof to listen to this music.
It's it's it's it's something to be it's a joyous thing is coming people coming together to enjoy that.
Where like I say, we've we've lost that with everything's faceless and no contact and don't touch.
It's about touching.
Yeah, it's about reaching out and touching the next person.
Do you know what I'm saying?
Yeah, slapping your mates back.
When you know, I mean, it's those little micro things that make the difference with us as a people.
Yeah, when we're told that that's bad and we shouldn't do this and we shouldn't connect,
that's when shit starts, excuse my language, but that's when stuff goes starts going wrong.
Yeah, you know, when we're connecting as a people, things get fixed.
Yeah, I'm a firm believer of that.
So you don't have to hold back on the podcast.
You can say whatever you want.
Yeah, I think connection is all we're creating, really.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's that. Yeah, that's life really is connection.
Absolutely.
You want to feel seen and you want to feel connection with other people.
Otherwise, what's the point?
Yeah, you're so right.
I'm like, I feel like the physical aspect is really interesting.
Like there aren't that many places in life where you can have like physically connect,
like like fighting.
We were talking about earlier, you know, like BJJ gym.
Like that's that's one way you kind of get very acquainted to people very quickly.
You know, sweating all over you.
And that raves a little bit similar, you know, like bumping into.
I don't know, like I feel like it's a healthy way to to connect with people
in some kind of physical fashion, sharing a drink.
Yeah. Do you know what I mean?
Like, you know, that was a thing of like, you know, back in the day,
people looking after each other.
You've got enough water.
You've got some water, like sharing a bottle of water,
just those little things that we just seem to have lost now.
Well, people do it within their own little micro sort of world with their friends.
Yeah. But it doesn't branch out
to the rest of the club, where it's it's it's all of us.
You look at any videos back in the day and everyone's tops off
arms around each other.
Yeah. You know, no one cared.
Do you know what I mean? Yeah.
Is that one of the main things you've noticed changing
that maybe people being a bit more self-conscious with the advent
of smartphones, that everything can be recorded because everyone's recording
what they're doing or they want to look the greatest for their 30 second
clip that they're going to post up telling them about their dinner
or what they're doing this day.
And I don't, you know, do you think you guys would have behaved differently
at other parties you were going to back in the day
if that was if that was something that was happening?
I'm not sure.
I think I think it's it's although it's really good for sharing information
and it's good for like connecting in a certain way, it's
it's also it's also isolating.
And it's unnatural.
Like if you look back just a hundred or two hundred years
before all this tech existed, we would have existed in a tribe
of 30 or 40 people in the community.
Yes. And if if the young if the young ones are misbehaving,
might get slap on the wrist and told, don't do this by one or two adults.
Yeah. And then they would learn from that and move on.
Was now a kid posts a picture of themselves on the Internet.
And they've instantly got potentially thousands of people commenting
and saying, oh, you're to this or you're to that.
And for a young developing brain, it's that's not natural
in any way, shape or form.
And I think that's why we're seeing such a rise in mental health issues
and all this stuff that's going on at the moment.
And I think music is potentially a cure for that because it's a reconnection.
It's a way of people coming back together.
Yeah. There's something I saw you say in a different interview, I think,
when you talk about like just that there are so few things in life
where everyone is experiencing the same thing at the same time.
Exactly. And they they're in the same kind of ballpark of caring about it,
like really caring about it and being like locked into it.
Yeah. Like that moment of unity, like between thousands of people.
Like when the drop kicks in the club, it's like we're all experiencing
those frequencies at the same time.
Yeah. That's it's magical.
And that's why the energy in those rooms sometimes is palatable.
Like, yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's like scratch and sniff.
It's like, what the fuck's going on? Yeah, crazy.
Yeah. But virus at Sealyard is like is and always will be
one of those kind of places for me that delivers that.
And like, I find it super interesting seeing people that, like,
have somehow wandered in there and don't have a connection to the scene.
Yeah, they're like, what's going on?
How they kind of transform over the course of the night.
And like, yeah, what that's like for them.
Yeah. Yeah.
Well, what the amazing thing is, is when you get a message from someone
that's like didn't listen to drummer bass, but for, you know,
before Saturday night, but oh, my God got dragged into Stealyard
for a virus and you've changed my life.
Oh, my God. Where have you been?
You know, yeah, they're the greatest messages because, you know,
let's face it, it's it's, you know, one seven.
Well, we make it a one seven four.
We're probably playing it at like one seven eight.
Yeah, it's fast. It's abrasive.
It's it's, you know, you have to really like it to lie.
Yeah. You know, I mean, it doesn't listen.
It's quite polarizing, isn't it?
Yes. Yeah.
People either love it or they really and they can decide that
quite quickly usually.
So, yeah, it's always interesting when someone's never been to a rave before.
And then you get that real sort of like light bulb moment
where they're like, oh, my God, this is great.
It's understandable as well, because if you're exposed to drum and bass
for the first time, let's say the first time you're hearing it is on a phone.
Yeah. Like tinny little thin speakers.
You've got no sub. Yeah.
There's no sub. You're like, oh, I'm not sure about this.
There's no horrible. It's almost horrible.
Yeah. And then you're stood in still yard or wherever you might be
in the middle of the floor and the subs moving your liver around.
And you're like, wow, wait a minute.
It's a totally different experience.
It feels like to me, like if I listen to tunes for a phone,
it feels like they've been neutered.
You know, like they can't have their balls chopped.
Yeah, that's it.
It is really a big percentage of listening to drum and bass is
listening to it in the right environment.
Yeah. You know, especially the stuff that we make.
It feels it feels kind of wrong to listen to it during the day.
Yeah, it has to be night time for me.
Like it for it to be just.
Yeah, it's just it just goes hand in hand with that.
And it has to be loud and bassy.
And that's also like when you're writing tunes,
you've got to kind of be thinking ahead.
But OK, I'm in a little room here.
This isn't the best environment to be listening to it.
But what's it going to be like at two o'clock in the morning
when you double drop it with whatever it might be?
It's like you're always kind of like in your mind's eye,
so to speak, kind of thinking potentially, how could this be?
Yeah. And I think you get better at that over time.
Just put in the hours, put in your 10k hours
and you can kind of start to figure that out a little bit,
navigate, navigate your experience in the studio a bit more effectively.
Yeah. Garth, you used this phrase like you felt like you were
like carving your name into the rock of drum and bass.
Like I love that phrase.
I'm imagining you like with this chisel just like
whacking away for like 10 years.
Yeah, that's just me like wanting to, you know, I just yeah,
I think that's just me talking about what I would like to have.
Whether I'm remembered or whatever, I just want to be.
I want my name with the stone, with all the other people that I class as
those people that sort of, you know, were big contributors
with drum and bass, you know, so yeah, that's just me.
Yeah, I know what you mean.
They're like kind of looking at the journey that you've been on.
Like I see I see someone with like a very like singular purpose.
Like, yeah, you know, you knew you wanted to be in this.
Yeah, you know, you're motivated.
Yeah, this is all I've ever wanted to do really from the moment
I sort of could figure out that I wanted to do something.
This was what it was.
Yeah. And you guys connected because like you called Ben, right?
Like you found a tape pack or something and like with a number on it
and you wanted to book him for a show.
Yeah. So in I think like beginning in 97, this was
I had a metal heads promo and on the back was was Joe.
He used to work for Metalhead.
He used to do sort of the doors for a lot of raves and stuff.
I literally we saw it at hospitality a few weeks ago.
And I told her this story because I was like, you know,
you just have to like realize that you're special to me.
So I literally rang this number and was like, hi,
I'd like to book Ed Rush.
How do I go? Had no clue.
And then Joe kindly was like, oh, let me give you his girlfriend's number.
Speak to her and you'll be able to book him.
And yeah, so me and my friends, we just we did a party
above a pub in Croydon, South Croydon.
We rented out like the function room, put a sound system in,
did flyers or whatever.
Majority of the people in the club were people we knew and friends.
We didn't get much walking trade. Yeah.
And then, yeah, Ben, yeah.
And then Ben, Ben turned up and blew the mixer up.
I was I was playing.
I was playing after him.
So he blew the headphone jack up.
So I had to DJ for an hour on vinyl with no headphones.
Well, I didn't care because I got to meet Ben.
And it was, you know, we felt that like, oh, my God,
we've not just put a party on with friends.
We put a party on and we booked. Yeah.
You know, the guy at the time,
because obviously Wurma was causing hype, it hadn't dropped yet.
But people knew it was coming and something.
The plates are getting played. So, yeah.
But yeah, that's how that's how I originally.
Met him outside a pub like, hi, I'm Gareth. Yeah.
And I know what that feels like.
All the stuff from like base camp and everything like that.
And he does like it's a bit of a surreal thing.
And it must be interesting for you kind of being on the other side.
Now, we're like, have you had this word like parasocial before?
You had that word.
Maybe. Yeah, it's kind of the word to describe like the
the feeling when someone is like a one sided relationship
where someone thinks that they know you or know about you
for all the stuff they put out there.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But you you've never met them before.
You like, you know, so it's very like one sided.
Yeah. And I guess as you've gone through your career,
like that's that's something that starts to develop more and more.
You know, there are people who are fans of music.
Yeah. They have some idea of who you are.
Well, what does what does that feel like for you guys?
Like must feel a bit strange, I guess.
Like, yeah.
Would you just not really think about it?
I don't I don't suppose I really think about it.
You know, I just I just do what I what I do, which is make music.
And that's the only way I can sort of describe it.
That's what I do.
That is, you know, if I if I if I'm relaxing
and I've got I'm not working at the weekend, I go in the studio.
If I'm during the week and I'm working, I go in the studio.
It's like it's the answer to everything.
My wife is having a conversation with me.
She was like, I was trying to describe what you do to a friend of hers.
He's not in the industry. He's in a different industry.
And it's it's just it is what I am.
Yeah. You're compelled to make music.
Yeah. It's just what I'm going to do.
Do you know what I mean?
Yeah. It's like a healthy obsession, isn't it?
Yeah. Yeah. I think that's, you know,
like like Gareth just said, I was the same when I was growing up.
I knew this is all I wanted to do.
And I had like two or three jobs just grinding to.
I was reading about you like driving a van one year.
Yeah. I used to work for Odbins, a wine company, delivering wine all day.
And then I was a butcher and a fishmonger.
I did some of the really shit jobs, but I just I just needed 12,
10 turntables. I needed to be able to just get on these.
I was just obsessed, obsessed.
This is obviously pre-production. Yeah.
And that's all I cared about.
I was going to do it no matter what.
Nothing's going to get in the way.
And and you know, and then you get them and then you learn how to beat match.
That took about four months locked in my bedroom.
All my mates are going to the pub and chatting up girls and doing all that.
I'm like, no, I'm just locked in.
This is all I want to do.
Oh, maybe you should come out. No, I'm not going anywhere.
I've got to figure these 12, 10s out.
I've got to figure out how to beat match, you know.
And back then, all the sequences were drifting.
Nothing stayed in time.
So we finally had to constantly ride the pitch and like
and those hours like that you that you put in are invaluable.
They're just they're like the backbone of everything.
And it teaches you like discipline and it teaches you like sacrifice.
You sacrifice time and you sacrifice maybe some of your social life.
And very often you sacrifice relationships as well.
But at the end of it, you come out with a skill set
and you come out with your obsession has paid off. Yeah.
Because then you kind of at the beginning of carving yourself a career.
And I think if you stick to it and you stay within
the healthy realms of the obsession, then, you know,
like the proofs in the pudding, you can it can become your life.
Yeah. And there was there was no shortcuts then.
Like there was no there's no YouTube.
You have to read the manual.
There's no there's nothing.
There's no one really giving you any information.
You know, I mean, I'm like, this is how you do this.
You see, there's none of that.
It's just watching other people.
Well, what's it? Why is he doing that?
Figuring it out.
Reverse engineering.
What's going on? Yeah.
And why people are doing certain things at certain points, you know,
and then that feeds into the production.
Yeah. It's ridiculously expensive.
Like to do it costs, you know, back then it was thousands of pounds
for the sampler, for a desk, a computer, sound modules, reverb,
delays, compressors.
Like it was it was like a mortgage for for a house, you know,
that us as 17, 18 year old kids want to do.
So it's just like you found, you know, your share in studios.
So that was like a filter almost for like
people that were not in it.
Yeah. For the right reasons left quite quickly because they wouldn't
make that sacrifice. They wouldn't make that sacrifice.
They wouldn't lose out on friends.
They wouldn't spend all the money, the disposable cash paying,
you know, paying debts and going record shopping once a month.
It was a real it's a real passion of love, you know,
and not saying that it's a bad thing having all that access now
and YouTube and tutorials and my God, there's a tutorial
to blow your nose out there.
You know, there's everything, you know,
that sometimes I think that you're missing out.
The joy is the exploration of these things.
And sometimes when you when you go straight from A to B,
sometimes it's the journey that's the good journey.
You know, that's the good bit.
That's where you really do the learning, not jumping from there
today and going, oh, I can make a sick race now.
I'm amazing. Doesn't work like that.
Yeah.
Well, I think over time, you know, the longer the journey,
you pick up skill sets along the way that help you
in all different environments, whereas if you just shortcut
it and all of a sudden you find your diaries full
and you're doing really well, you might have a great year
because you made a big tune and you have been producing that long.
But you might not be able to
maybe socialize in a healthy way, or you might have
attitude problems and being ironed out yet.
And you end up pissing off the wrong promoter
and you never get you know, there's like
there's certain skill sets that you learn from putting in the grind
that come over time.
It's a complex animal, this the scene, isn't it?
Yeah, different, different sides to it.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. You've got to be able to work people, not work people,
but know how to talk to people, you know, know how to sort of,
you know, like the situation now, a lot of kids are
they're coming from relative obscurity.
And like Ben says, getting a massively kind of catapulted
almost getting a full diary, earning lots of money
and they don't know how to talk to people.
You don't know, you know, they're not talking.
They don't know. You talk to everyone exactly the same.
The janitor or the CEO, you talk to them exactly the same.
Yeah, they have the same level of respect for everyone.
And some people walk in and they don't have that.
And you can just see that they're not going to last long
because it's not just how bad you are on the decks
or how sick you are in the studio.
It's a real melting pot of like of human traits
that I think to be successful.
I know a lot of people that care a lot.
100 percent. Otherwise, it's going to be a flash in the pan.
You could tell a lot from a person, from how they talk to
like a waitress or a waiter like that.
Literally, you can see the character there and then,
you know, the amount of people that I've been out to dinner with
before a show or whatever.
And there's one DJ or maybe a couple and they're just
rude to the waiting staff.
And it's embarrassing. You know, you're like.
You know, you so people expose their characters in these
in these little snippets of life,
these little these little Polaroid moments.
Yeah. So that's what you're about.
And you're a wanker.
Yeah. Yeah. You're an asshole.
Basically, it's funny when people that they don't realise
that they're talking to maybe someone who's someone who's
significant in that space, you know, they don't realise
and they conduct themselves in a certain way.
And then, yeah, then actually the light bulb goes on
and they're like, oh, shit, it's like deer in headlights.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Mad.
I was going to ask, so relate some of the grassroots
promoted stuff I've been involved in over the years.
I've often been the guy going and getting the rider on
nights. I was going to ask you, this kind of comes back
to respect as well.
What's the silliest thing you've seen someone put on their rider?
Underwear, underwear.
Yeah, I think it's quite good, though.
Functional or like underwear, like pants and socks.
Yeah. And I kind of.
I thought, why are you doing that?
I mean, you know, if you're playing around Europe or the UK,
it's a bit weird. But if you're on tour in America,
I guess I get it.
And you've got one little bag.
I'm like, yeah, OK, it makes sense.
Fresh socks every day. Yeah.
Makes sense. Yeah.
A mask, I think. A mask.
Like a COVID one. Just a different.
No, like a mask.
Well, like Zorro or whatever.
Whatever. That was not specified.
Unspecified. Unspecified mask.
And it's from actually from quite a big person.
Really? Yeah. Huge person, actually, in Drama Base.
Yeah. And that was on the.
I don't know if it's still there.
It probably changed now to Caviar and whatever.
But it was a mask.
It was a mask.
Yeah, I was like a regular thing.
Or it was just a one off.
No, it was no, it was apparently it was it was that was it.
Yeah. And I think someone else didn't want someone from Bad Company
have a blow up boat.
A little dinghy.
I'm sure it was.
That's like an Aoki move.
I don't know. Yeah, I don't know.
I'm sure. I'm sure it was Maldini or Vegas.
I might have got that wrong, boys.
Sorry if it's not.
I might have got that completely wrong, but I swear one of them had.
You're going to get flame leads.
I'm not seeing that many.
The mask was the most unusual thing.
I'm clutching for why blow up boat like crowd surfing maybe.
I don't know. I don't know why.
How many opportunities you get to do that at Drama Base.
If you're at Horsespotality on the beach, like I kind of see maybe
you'd be like, do you want one of those rubber rings or something?
That's quite a bespoke scenario there.
But yeah, the mask was quite interesting, but that's about it for me.
I took it and got like a full watermelon.
For an artist once. Nice.
Yeah, that's quite a good idea.
Yeah, but like when you got to carry all this stuff back from the shop.
Yeah, no, it's fucking heavy, aren't they?
It's like, can you not pick a smaller fruit?
Was there a bottle of vodka as well and they were maybe going to fill
the watermelon with vodka because that's quite a good one.
I've got to mention, honourable mention to Connor, Emperor,
who had an amazing rider when I went to, I was in Toulouse with him
a few weeks ago and he had like protein bars, like mint tea.
It was just like the health.
It was like.
Times have changed.
It was the healthiest option ever.
It was just like, oh my God, are you going on a run after this?
Like, are you bulking before a gym workout?
Like, what is going on?
Yeah, so honourable mention Connor.
Very good Connor.
Well done.
I hope we haven't inspired you to take your rider in some weird
and wonderful directions with the Valkyrie show.
Yeah, now that you're going to be the one going out and getting it.
Oh God, yeah.
A couple of watermelons and a flower, hopefully.
Tell us a bit about that show, you know, looking forward to that.
Have you played Lightbox before?
Yes, you have done.
Yeah, I don't think I have actually.
Yeah, it's cool.
So yeah, it's the one that has the ceiling that all lights up.
Yeah, really good.
Really nice.
Not too big, quite an intimate vibe in there.
Good sound system.
Nicely located.
I think it's a good choice.
Yeah, I'm hyped.
And if I remember, the booth is quite good as well.
It's like a decent experience.
Like, yeah, I think it's a good one.
Should be good.
Looking forward to it.
It's gonna be nice to meet some of the community as well.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Be good.
I think, yeah, meet me and greet to kick things off.
I don't know.
Like, it's part of this whole community thing that we want to push.
Like, because everything feels like it's getting less personal.
I just want to inject a little bit of that back end.
100%, we love that.
It'll be interesting to see how people take to that.
Yeah.
I think they're ready for it.
I'll be honest.
I think they genuinely want that, but sometimes don't know how to.
You just need to kind of throw yourself in and try.
Someone just has to do it and then go, oh, okay.
This is cool.
I can act like this.
You know what I mean?
Or I can come and say hello to you.
And it's just like, yeah, I'm just a guy.
Yeah.
Do you know what I mean?
It's like, I'm not this awful thing that's going to bite your head off.
Just ask me a question and we'll have a chat.
An axe carrying guy from the promo.
Give that person around, but it's really not what I'm about.
But no, yeah.
How's it going with the WhatsApp group?
Is it?
It's good, man.
Yeah.
It's hard to keep track of sometimes.
You know, like we got hundreds of messages a day.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
And I know you guys have been quite active with kind of setting things up.
Maybe tune writing.
I've heard people making songs, setting challenges and stuff.
Yeah.
Like, so this is the bunch of kind of like developing producers.
Like, you know, who we're mates with, who's kind of part of our group.
I don't know, like I used to like teach like a very, very basic
like music production thing in the base camp community.
Just like the very basics for people who wanted to try for the first time.
And we used to do like a weekly challenge with that as a way to encourage people
to like practice what we were talking about.
Yeah.
I just wanted to kind of bring a little bit of that flavour to kind of what we're doing.
So it's a bit more kind of intermediate producers, I would say, in the group.
Yeah.
You know, anyone can get involved.
We just like this thing called like Silly Sunday, where literally like,
I don't know, find some weird sample off YouTube.
Brilliant.
Or like, I don't know, like spin a wheel and like remix this genre.
Yeah.
You know, stuff like that.
And I don't know, just something to...
That's really cool.
So kind of almost like bring a bit of the collaborative vibe
or even just the conversation around production.
Make it a bit less insular and, you know what I mean?
A bit less serious as well, right?
And it doesn't have to be so heavy.
Yeah, exactly.
Because my drum base is fun.
Well, music is fun, ultimately.
You know what I mean?
That's why we do it, isn't it?
Ultimately, it's like, it's fun and to have a good time
and to release a few demons and feel better and, you know,
so yeah, it's great.
And like, Ben, like collaboration like in the studio,
like that's where you came from, right?
They were like, no U-turn kind of era and like being in the cupboard
with Matt like back in the day.
Yeah, literally in St.
Anne's Court in Soho there where we wrote Wormhole.
Yeah.
Rob Playford had a studio there and he had a broom cupboard
and was like, I'm not using this cupboard.
I know you guys don't have a room.
Do you want a cup?
And it was the most amazing sounding room
because it was small and tight
and we put carpet all over the walls in the ceiling.
So it was dead in there.
So yeah, lots of lots of collaboration in my in my career.
Yeah, I guess that's which we're just trying to engineer
and find ways to kind of create some of those connections
because like, you know, like London real estate stuff is
it's not the same as it was like you can't get space easily.
Like people aren't always like in such close proximity together.
Yeah, but I think we like we recognize like everyone
like you feed off each other's energy like ideas.
Yeah, you know, someone someone gives you a sample
or some sounds whatever and you go and do something completely different.
It's easier to collab now than it was
because back in the day you had to literally be in the same room.
So physically it was more restricting.
Now you can be you can collab with someone in Australia in the UK
like just from stem bouncing or there's even these plugins
you can put on your master and they put on their master
and the changes happen in real time as long as you're in the same door.
That's mad.
So as they're changing the project your project updates as well,
which is really cool.
Have you guys used something like that together?
Not yet. I've heard about it.
I'm really curious to try it.
You just want to slam something into the clipper.
Like this time around we did we did approach it differently.
Like we've this time around sort of I would start something stem that out
like, you know, build a rough intro and perhaps a 32 of the drop
and then stem that out and then send that to Ben to finish
and go, you know, do your thing and then he would do the same to me
where before all the other killbox stuff was was done pretty much
in the same room.
We'd meet we'd meet once once a week and do stuff
and you get these positives and negatives for both of those experiences
doing it online and being in the same room.
You know, I mean we talked about yesterday as well.
Like if you're in the same room, sometimes you don't want to be
sort of indulgent and spend too long on something because
you're conscious that is someone else in the room
and you want to keep that energy up where when you're on your own
and you're just bouncing stems, you're like you're getting excited about
oh, what's he going to make of this bit?
Oh my god.
This is this is cool.
I hope he likes this bit.
And so it's it's I think there's good to really nerd out
when you're on your own just over one patch just dial it in
like four hours.
It's fine.
Yeah, whereas you don't want to keep someone waiting for four
hours while you're but this but there's nothing quite like
being in the studio which I've done a lot in my in my past
with, you know, working with other people.
I did a dubstep group with three other people that we picks
Yeah, that was all in the same studio every Wednesday and would
write music and there's a buzz when there's four of you
all jumping around.
Yeah, you know, I mean, you know, like the whole the
whole, you know, the room is getting that kinetic energy
because you're you're like, yeah, this is getting somewhere
and this is not just a kick and a snare and a loop.
Now.
This is actually this is a vibe.
Yeah, and then like try this.
Oh, what about this?
And what reverse that vocal and do it and then you like
and it's just a melting pot of ideas.
And I guess like instant feedback as well.
It's not it's not just your own opinion and like getting
locked on in a loop somewhere like, you know, you're
seeing real-time what works what people vibe with.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think as far as amount of work goes though,
I think the the stemming approach has been more
prolific for us just being able to get tunes done
and get projects finished and move on to the next.
Yeah, and I think once you've been making music
for a certain amount of time and you're working with
someone whose taste is very similar someone that you
trust there's not too much worry about if I send this
off and it comes back.
I might not like it.
You know, you're going to like it.
Yeah, you know, so that that just serves for getting
things done a bit quicker because as you saw within
two months, we've written like eight tunes.
Yeah, I'm like that's that was my first experience
of like seeing you guys kind of going off and
working and like doing that.
That's like the creative process.
Yeah, like it surprised me like with how fast the
ideas were coming back.
Yeah, like how well formed they were like the
tunes still evolved and they still changed as you
approach the final almost the crux of the ideas.
Yes, just experience just knowing, you know,
you've got your setups in your door, you know,
where things should hit on the spectrum and you're
just like, yeah, if this is going to translate on
a rig, I know this needs to be here and this
needs to be here.
We both pretty much follow the same rule.
So I know if I send something from my room to
him, it's going to sound okay in his room and
vice versa.
It's like cross compatible.
You're not like, yeah, and we're always talking
about production between us.
Like if I learn something new, I'm keen to tell
him and you know, if he's find some new sick
plug-in or whatever, or he's found some
technique, he tells me so we're constantly
learning together, which is also important because
it just means that you get to the point you
need to be a lot quicker.
I always want to ask Ben, so like your
solo album, like the standard of like
neuro production these days is amazing.
Like it's insane.
I guess everything that people being through
like the noisy guys pushing everything forward
engineering wise, all of the new techniques,
new plugins, like you guys both come from
the hardware era and like, you know, you
you've been evolving as producers, but like
that that was the first time that you
did like a big solo project.
Yeah, you know, you kind of put yourself
out there, put it on the line.
Yeah, and you're suddenly now competing
like at that level with these other guys.
Like what was that like for you?
Like what was that process of kind of
like, like leveling up, you know, to be
in that arena?
That was one of the benefits of COVID
really was the fact that I was stuck
in my house for so long.
All those rules that I'd learned in
the analog world that Matt and I were
doing that aren't applicable and don't
work in the digital world.
Like it's so easy just to hold onto
those and be like that was the era.
This was the golden time.
And yeah, but you know, times change
dramatically and the way that people
make music has changed.
So I had to unlearn all those rules
and relearn everything else and it
was just finding the time to do it.
And COVID just allowed this huge
amount of time for me just to sit
and just really kind of get to
the crux of it all and try and
learn the techniques and what works
in this new digital world and
what doesn't I mean, I was kind
of halfway there before COVID
but didn't wasn't I just wasn't
happy with sharing my music with
anyone or playing them in my own
set. So we just kind of sat on
my hard drive.
Was that kind of like the sort of
scarabs era?
Yes, exactly.
And I think I was also like
testament to your hard work as
well because you did it takes
graft to come from a certain
position and almost play
catch-up because I was already
in the digital world.
I was doing stuff and I was
a solo artist predominantly
before that.
So I was sort of already there.
So then to watch Ben come
from where he was to where he
is now is incredible.
It's incredible and to do it at,
you know, we're not spring
chickens.
Do you know what I mean?
But like we're not, you know,
we've got families and lives
and stuff to go on and the
manage that he managed to get
to that level at this point
is commendable really is.
Thanks mate.
It comes down back to the
obsession thing again.
I was just, failure wasn't an
option.
I'm like I need to be able
to do this.
I've got these ideas.
Yeah, I want to be able to
play my own tunes in my set
and stuff and like the only
way to do it is just to grind
and just to get to that point
and ask lots of questions
and you know, Patreon is
helpful.
There is stuff on YouTube
that's helpful and just
trial and error.
Just try this.
Try that.
A lot of phone calls with
him and like, you know,
and yeah, just really just
grinding.
That's all it was.
Just putting in the hours
again.
It was like re-learning
again, which was the
struggle because it's so easy
just to fall back into those
old habits, just red light
everything.
Oh fuck it, it's going to
sound alright.
But as we all know, you do
that in the computer and it
just sounds like trash.
Yeah.
And now like a couple of
years on like, how do you
kind of like look back at
that, that solo album?
Like the dust has kind of
settled a bit.
Like, yeah, I'm, I'm proud
of it.
I still wish I could have
another go.
That's nearly turned up
loud.
That's a bit too loud.
Exactly.
I wish I could go back on
half the tunes and retweet
them and maybe turn.
But the funny thing is
like I heard you talk
before about like back in,
back in the day when
you were working on
tapes, like, you know, when
the desk was set up in a
certain way, like, you know,
you, you had to commit.
Yeah.
It was one.
It was one, one, one,
one desk.
You would never have that
mix again, even if you
took like, I mean, you
couldn't even have a phone
to take pictures.
So we would have like
photocopies of all the
dials and you would just
go, oh, that was at 12
o'clock.
That was a one o'clock
that week.
Tape.
We used to use tape.
Yeah.
Just put a little bit of
tape on the faders.
Yeah.
Like valves warming up on
the compressors.
Like it's all, all these
things were like made
fundamental differences to
what you were doing.
If the desk was warm,
if it's cold outside,
yeah, the electronics
were, valves were cold.
It would just, yeah,
it was.
So you almost had to
like, you know, there
was a writing process
and then the mixing
process.
And once you thought
you were in the right
ballpark, it's very
often a case of like
you've got to just
leave it for a couple
of days because you
bound, you know, you'd,
you'd, you'd put that
mix on that.
You'd listen to it and
you'd listen to it
again.
You listen to it again
and then you come back
the next day, maybe
tweak a little bit.
But after two days,
that was it because you
need to write more stuff.
Yeah.
So you got to move on
to the next project.
Yeah.
So then just reset
and then that's it.
There's no recall.
There's no chance of
tweaking anything.
Again, you're committed.
It's quite nice like that though
because it's like,
it's like catching the
magic in the,
in the bottle.
You know what I mean?
Like you, you, you,
you catch these mixes
and you would have,
you know, you'd talk
about it like you,
you don't know it.
You'd have certain sessions
where it just is,
you're just like they,
what they describe flow
state now.
You're just, the tracks
almost right in itself.
Yeah.
Do you know what I mean?
It's telling you
what has to happen next.
Yeah.
And ultimately when you
find at the end of them
sessions, the mix is
pretty good as well.
Yeah.
Because you're just in that.
You're just dialed in.
You're just into this tune.
You're not being,
you know, you're just,
you know exactly what
happened, what needs to happen,
what volume this needs to be.
Yeah.
And do you feel like
some of that experience
has kind of like
carried you through
into the way you work now
in the digital era,
Gareth?
Yeah.
Like being maybe a bit less
of like a tweaker.
You're like with your
VSTs and stuff
versus like committing.
Yeah.
I'm a great believer
in like less is more.
Like, and having less
equipment forces more
creativity.
Yeah.
I believe so.
Instead of having,
you know, lots of
reverbs and lots
of delay VSTs
and lots of this,
I have one
re, one reverb,
one delay,
maybe two delays I use.
A couple of distortion
units, but that's it.
I don't have massive
banks of this anyway.
Yeah.
Because it,
once you simplify
all of that,
then the ideas can
really start.
If you're relying on
like, oh, this,
this new VST does
this particular thing
really cool.
And I'll add that
to the end of the chain
and that will do that.
It will do its little
signature thing to my sound.
Yeah.
Yeah. Like an artist
isn't like obsessing
over like when a new
paintbrush is going
to come out, right?
Yeah.
You know what I mean?
Like, yeah,
it's just a blank
piece of paper
and it doesn't
matter what it is.
It's just, you know,
and I think that's
they're your tools
and mechanic walks
into, you know,
a garage.
There's a size 10 spanner
and a flathead
screwdriver.
Oh, he's good.
Like off he goes.
Yeah.
You watch these videos
as well and they're like
we've got four EQs
and we're stacking them all.
We're running the same
break beat through them all
and then here's
plus 10k on this one
and here's plus 10k.
To me they all sound
the same.
Yeah.
Like,
and they're like,
oh, if you can't hear
the difference,
then your ears need training.
It's like you just
need one EQ,
the EQs
that you're familiar with
that works well.
And like he said,
one reverb is the
only way.
Otherwise you just,
you just get lost
in the source and you're
getting bogged down
and you're killing
the creativity time,
aren't you?
You're nerding out of,
I think once in a while
there's a breakthrough
in technology
and there's a new
plugin that comes through
that changes the game.
Like shape of box
is amazing.
It changes how we side
chain and we use
that on everything.
There's this new
side chaining they're doing
now that's like
ring modulation side
chain.
And that's great.
I didn't have it before.
It's essential now.
I need it.
So once in a while
these things come along,
but they work their way
into your template
and they become part of
your, you know,
apparatus for working.
And I think then
every once in a while
a new like synth
might drop
and that will give you
inspiration for,
you might not use it
forever,
but for a week
or a few days
you're on it
and there's these new patches
and you're like
might get a nice
lead out of it
or a nice arp
or something
and it kind of
pushes you in a direction
you wouldn't normally go.
So I think that's cool
and that's healthy.
But nerding out over
what EQ you should use.
I think you should just
probably just use the one
that's in your door
to be honest.
Looking back
it kind of feels like
there was almost like
a tech arms race
in music.
You know what I mean?
Like
I was kind of
of that generation
that was going out
like when Skrillex
dropped his EP
and was really getting
into FM8 and Massive
and you know like
all the DMB artists
were getting into Massive
and doing this stuff
and I don't know
if you guys agree.
It kind of feels like
there's like a
diminishing returns
with this.
Like
there's always going to be
innovation and creativity
but like maybe
maybe just like
exploring the world.
There's still
undiscovered places
but less of them.
Yeah.
Does that kind of
resonate with you guys?
Yeah.
You were making
dub stuff as well
I guess.
Yeah.
That whole world
of sound design
like has
do you take some of that
stuff through into
DMB as well?
Yeah I'll tell you
everything's a learning
experience.
You know
interactions with my son
and my daughter
and my wife are
things that I pull
into Drum and Bass.
So yeah everything
I think
I don't think you can
rule anything out.
I think working in
different genres
is healthy.
Doing some
different stuff.
Yeah.
Because you end up
with different
sound palettes
that you wouldn't
normally have before
and you're like
oh this might
work in this
or being able
to drag stuff in
for maybe even
if it's just
for an intro
or something
but it's something
that you wouldn't
normally have
if you were just
writing on
7-4 Drum and Bass.
What are some
of those genres
that you like
ban like outside of
DMB?
What would you
like listen to?
I mean I
I like all
music in general
but as far as like
my personal production
I've made some
house tunes before
that I like
like tech house
minimal tech house
kind of sounds
and I've written
loads of kind of
like hip-hop stuff
like trap
kind of
trappy stuff.
Yeah.
Well like 808s
and like kind of
yeah.
Actually during
Covid
a friend of mine
was kind of
trying to push
this artist
this American
R&B singer
and she was
doing an
album project
and I got like
six of my tunes
on there
that I just like
130, 140
trappy stuff
R&B style
and that was really
cool because I was doing
working with
melody
and stuff I never
really worked
with before
and having to
kind of think
in a different way
rather than how
is this going to
drop on the
dance floor
thinking about
how is this
going to
evoke emotion
and how is this
going to
I mean all
music should
have emotion
right but
when you're
writing
neuro
it's pretty
much one
emotion.
Big bad
dangerous.
Yeah that's
it.
So I had to
think about
chords
and you know
G minor
is it a
sad chord
and all that
kind of
stuff was really
interesting for me
so I enjoyed
that a lot
that was cool.
Yeah and
it's it's
interesting here
when you say
that like
I think there
were a couple
of tracks
on your
album where
you kind of
got to
almost like
explore a
home listening
vibe a
bit more
though it
didn't just
have to
be a
club
record right.
Yeah,
there was
scope on
there that was
a vocal
thing that
was like
kind of
similar to
what she's
talking about
kind of a
bit more
emotive
and more
melodic
and kind of
had sort
of chords
in it
wee.
I did that
pre-Covid
I did an
album that
was not
based on
that muscle
of like
what does
me making
a home
listening
album
so you
just adapt
don't you
at the time
and the
play we
weren't
going to
club
so you
the creativity
comes out
just in
different
and you
just point
in a
different
slightly
direction
you know
yeah.
Whilst we're
talking about
creativity
and style
I actually
got a few
questions
from there
from the
community
from my
WhatsApp.
I know
there was
from the
WhatsApp group.
Yeah.
I don't know
if I can
ask all
of them
but there
was one
like that
I wanted
to ask
so
I want
PG enough.
Yeah.
What one
is PG enough.
So
my mate
Jay
so shout out
who's
actually
making
some
visuals
for
your
show
for
that
day
yesterday
big
up
Monday.
He was
saying in
your
words
how
do you
describe
your own
signature
sounds
like
each
of you
and then
how does
that
change
when you
collaborate
interesting.
I would
say
I mean
my
sound
has
changed
over the
years
right
it was
kind of
back
in
like
the
late
90s.
It was
definitely
more
it's more
jungly
more.
Yeah more
jungly
more funky
more space
in it
lot more
breakbeats
being used
so there's
an actually
more groove
and shuffle
in those
but I
think now
the stuff
I'm
making
is
just
pretty much
geared
towards
the dance
floor.
So
I'd
say
I don't
know
it's
hard man.
That's
a
tough
one.
I
guess
it's
kind of
a lot
yeah
it's
morphed
from
kind of
like
more
traditional
funky
neuro
funk
to
just
kind of
dance floor
neuro funk.
It's
like a
Darwin
like
evolution
you know
toward
towards
like
being the
apex
predator
in the
club
environment.
Yeah.
I mean
Fresh said
something
years ago.
It's
like the
space
between
the
notes
are
just
as
important
as the
notes
that
are
in
the
tune
and that
kind of
sticks
with me
as well.
I think
it's
important
but
yeah
interesting
question
and what
about you
Gareth
like
signature
sounds
like
and
and then
how
they
combine
I think
I've always
been a
bit
I think
it's
always
been
raw
and uncompromising
I think
my
my music
from
from the
very
first
you know
from my
first
album
on
Tech Freaks
and doing
therapy
sessions
and
that
whole
sort of
part of
my
journey
that was
as hard
as you
could get
at that
that point
so
yeah
pretty
and I don't
really
I don't
I don't think
I've strayed
too far
from the
path
to be
honest
with you
it's
just
techniques
have
got
better
and
sharper
you
know
I can
make
the
bass
hit
a bit
heavier
and
drums
a
slice
a bit
sharp
you know
I
I do
because
I don't
I think
if you
listen
to
something
from
that
album
that I
did
you know
whatever
something like
that
album
and you
listen
to the
stuff
now
really
that
the sentiment
that they're
both
portraying
is
the
same
it's
just
one's
technically
done
a bit
better
than
the other
I think
you've
got
more
depth
in your
music
now
than you
had
back
then
yeah
another
like
warehouse
and
those
like
there
was
like
one
idea
going
around
in a
loop
balls
to the
wall
I think
now
all that
rave
machine
with
Baroque
yeah
I mean
that's just
delving back into
the sort of
the history
of raving
and listening
to
listening
to sort
of that
sort of
stuff
but
yeah
I've
definitely
like
as
and
as you
get
older
and
do
music
more
you
learn
more
you know
your
palette
grows
with
your
skill
set
do you
know
what I
mean
it's
just
like
I can
try
and do
this
I can
try
and do
this
I can
so
yeah
perhaps
I've
just
expanded
it
I think
but
at the
I still
like
very
hard
aggressive
music
and
sampling
as well
like
love
sampling
yeah
I've
heard you a bit
of a
Wutan
yeah
love
that shit
so
I can still
hit like
all of that
let
samples
sprinkled
in like
give me a
track personality
like
yeah
definitely
I'm a
sucker
if I find
a little
string
loop
that I can
kind of
time up
and get
in
and a little
hip-hop
vocal
it's
in the
track
like
I love
that
shit
you know
I mean
a lot of our
U-turn stuff was
heavily
influenced by
that we had
lots of
Wu-Tang
samples
and
you know
Method Man
and all
those guys
in there
as much
as we could
probably couldn't
get away
with it
as much
now but
back then
that was
main
sampling
was like
we just
go to
our
hip-hop
libraries
yeah
I feel
like there's
there's still
a bit of
that spirit
left in
D&B
like almost
that rebellious
like
probably
shouldn't
do this
but
yeah
but we
might
get away
with it
you know
like
you can
kind of
fly under the
radar
yeah
a bit
well
if you
twist it
enough
they won't
recognize it
just
ram it
through
trash
and
like
it just
unrecognizable
prove it
wasn't
me that
said those
yeah
and
delivered it
exactly
like
Method Man
did
yeah
okay
all right
what else
we got
from the
community
Steve
Steve was
asking
for your
trash
settings
Gareth
but I
feel like
that might
be a
trade
secret
I don't
know
like
the
trash
because
I'm not
biggest
I don't
use
trash
that much
to be
fair
I don't
use it
that
a great
deal
yeah
I'm
not
it's
really
my
I'm
still
a camel
fat
guy
I'm
still
camel
fat
bit of
rift
tantrum
is
good
tantrum
I really
like
yeah
tantrum
is really
cool
rift
is
really
cool
tantrum
has got
a nice
almost
analogue
texture
to it
yeah
a bit
like
camel
fat
yeah
camel fat
is
man
it's just
undeniably
the one
how many
people
sit like
you know
it's the
goat
one
still
digging
it
like
resurrecting
this
plug
in
which
isn't
supported
anymore
it's
not
support
luckily
that
I
bought
it
I have
they're
literally
kept
in a
separate
hard drive
vault
that's
in the
safe
do you
know what I mean
and when
I get
a new
PC
it's
like
unlock
install
camel fat
will it
work
yes
it still
works
yeah
it's
amazing
how
no one's
better
day
over
all
these
years
yeah
or
it's
the
familiarity
that
we've
had it
it's
been
like
you
know
it's
like
that
best
friend
that's
never
let
you
down
do you
know
what I mean
it's
like
that
good
old
reliable
boys
never
you
know
I mean
Burr
Oaks
still
swear
by
it
they put in
every tune
yeah
it's like
it's
everyone's
using it
camel fats
the one
yeah
I don't know
it's
interesting
so
yeah
the trash
two is
good
trash
two is
cool
but
yeah
it's
not my
go to
it's
there
in the
library
but like
I said
I probably
have two
or three
that I really
use
a lot
and it's
camel fat
rift
and tantrum
and it's
got nice
clipper
control
I think it's
called
clip control
in trash
two
that's
nice
yeah
it's just
like a
really
but it sounds
really cool
yeah
and there's one
called
crunchy
taco
yes
that's
quite
nice
yeah
there's another
one
I think
it's
called
sand paper
yeah
that's
nice
for kind
of gritty
top end
it's very
extreme
I find
trash
where sometimes
I don't
want it
to be
yeah
you can
I want
to build
up a little
bit
that
extremeness
over
a
an
amount
of like
stacking
VSTs
I don't
want to
go
like
straight
from
A to
B again
yeah
like
zero to
the
journey
through
to
to B
is
the
exciting
bit
where
you'll
pull
the
harmonics
out
and
EQ
and then
distort
you'll
start
going
an
interesting
way
then
add
a bit
of
movement
and
so
yeah
there's
not
one
that
does
it
all
I think
just
adding
loads
of them
all
doing
a little
thing
yeah
is
the
way
yeah
sounds
good
one thing
I want to
ask
so
back
back in
the
day
so
Ben you did almost like an exchange with the Ram Trilogy guys where you like swapped a couple of tunes each
and then you made this like kind of smash these tunes together and like remix them into one tune
oh I love them days mate I love the days of two tunes into one
which I think is such a cool idea like
yeah
I don't really see that happening anymore
it doesn't happen anymore
so I want to ask you guys like if you could pick like another producer like or some guys people to work with
and do that concept again who would you pick and why
to give them like
oh do you know no did
did
they did
what was the flip side to
crisis
they did lifespan and crisis
life crisis
and they did it together
and in the second drop it's flipped into
we did mind
scanners
mines
mine
mine scan
mine scan remix
yeah
and you did scanners and mind overload
yeah we sent that to them and then they were like
ah
okay
and then they stuck the two together as well
yeah
it was
yeah it was quite interesting because we
we
they sent us the samples for both and we like well we like
we want to use this from this and this from this
so let's just do like a
yeah
like a jive bunny
love it
yeah
I don't know who I'll do now though
yeah that's tough
I mean burrow obviously spring to mind
I was watching them at virus and they're open with perfect drugs
yeah they did
and they did something too
I don't know what they did to it
they did a little mix
they did
that was a little
was it like a mash up or
no no they did a little
bootleg
yeah
that was a great moment
it was amazing
yeah
because they were really excited to play it to us as well
you could see like they wanted to share that
they felt like they were kind of keeping this big secret or something
yeah exactly
yeah yeah
almost like a bit naughty like they're doing it in front of you
yeah exactly
yeah
yeah that was a cool moment
you didn't feel the urge to throw him down some stairs
for having to go one of your jeans
I want it
I'm like you better send it to me
I want to play it
yeah
don't gate keep this one
I don't know who I'd do
I don't know who I would do it with to be honest with you
doesn't have to be drum and bass
could be
yeah I was thinking maybe someone non
non drum and bass
Wu-Tang then
yeah
yeah I'd do Wu-Tang
yeah get direct access to all the songs
yeah yeah yeah protect your neck and fucking something else
I've always wanted to make a tune with Sonny
I think it'd be cool to do something with Skrillex
that would be amazing
get him on a neuro drum and bass thing like
I think that would be really cool
I heard he's got like a whole
unreleased album
unreleased with the Noisier guys
yeah yeah
like a rock
yeah
like a pendulum-esque
yeah and I guess for whatever reason
you know I guess he's sort of moved on in his career and maybe
maybe that feels
I think he wrote it
a relic or something
yeah
and then
during that project he did Monsters
yeah
Deadmau5 heard that and said
I want that
yeah
but I need some more tunes to go with it
for an EP
so he did some other
Dunstep stuff
Monsters are nice sprites
yes
yeah
and then that became his sound
so all of a sudden this kind of rock
drum and bass hip-hop thing that he'd done
didn't fit that mould
and I think he's kind of carved his path into that
and that became his thing
so yeah I've heard about this album as well
I really want to hear it
yeah
hopefully it'll see the light of day
I hope so
like
I feel like this
at some point
you still get some little glimmers of that kind of like
dub plate culture
yeah
in our scene like
you know the unreleased records and
it's so exciting like for me
like that's why I wanted to go out to shows to hear unreleased music
yeah
and to have that special moment where
you hear something before anyone else has ever heard it
yeah
it's the most important
it's the most
it's one of the driving forces for me is to
like especially for a virus party
yeah
like I need to roll up to that party
with at least four or five things that no one's heard
yeah
just to feel like
okay I'm ready
yeah
and it was and it's same for Let It Roll
like I always used to write
like an intro track for Let It Roll sets
it's just yeah
I think it's special
I think if you make that effort it's
you know
it's part of the culture
people notice
it's part of the culture as well
people do notice
dub plate culture has been engraved in our scene from Day Dot
yeah
you know from the from the Sound Clash era
it's kind of it's part of our thing
so I think it's it's
it's essential
and I think it's really interesting
seeing like a new generation almost like instinctively reaching
for it
but finding it hard to do that
so like
Annie like
on her data transmission like interview
like
I was at her flat
and we were like
what will she she put at the end of this interview
like for the like any other thoughts
and she'd been so obsessed with that Killa B's remix
like we went to virus together
and she would not stop talking about this Killa B's remix
like for months afterwards
and we're like just just put like tell audio to release
the Killa B's remix
but then you send it to her
yeah, yeah, yeah
you saw that thing right
and yeah, yeah, yeah
and like
I think that's really interesting
because there's love coming back
and there's someone appreciating what I've done
and that's all it needs
I don't need
monetary
I just need someone to recognize sometimes that
I appreciate what you did
do you know what I mean
or I appreciate
I get comments on stuff the other day
and this this girl would
and she was talking about the last virus party
and she was like
and she just commented on like
oh, it's so nice to hear someone play
like loads of new shit
that I've not heard before
and like that really
like make that made my day
that comment
I don't need specifics
I just need someone to recognize that
yeah
oh that work you put in
I heard it
do you know what I mean
and like that was really like
and it was amazing for me
but yeah, yeah
I'm gonna of course
and she used to wear a little B outfit
didn't she
yeah
a B costume has been worn in Stereo
I can confirm
I don't know if it's been retired now
or
no
I hope not
if bits of it are still lit
yeah, we'll bring it back out
bring it back out
that's classic
yeah
whilst we're here
yeah, Ben
Piranha Pool
I wanted to ask a little bit about that
yeah
it's almost like
a little bit of a secret
for like the new generation
they might not know
that you've gone out and done that
yeah
tell us a little bit more about it
because like the details are quite scarce
scarce out there
I mean it's only ever had one release
it's only had two
because it was scarabs
plus like shapes released on it as well
right
no
it's just scarabs
maybe I've got that wrong
yeah
it's just scarabs
I mean yeah
it was just basically
I wanted a platform to start putting my own music out
and
so I thought
you know
it's a good idea maybe to do it
but in order to do it properly
and to really have like
a label that's gonna make a difference
it really is a huge commitment
it's hard work
and you need a team
behind you and stuff
and there were so many other projects on the go
you know I was working with Gareth
and
kind of
it was
it was just
I think I could
utilize it again
I think it's gonna come back
maybe it's a platform for up-and-coming talent
and for putting some of my own stuff out again
but
I just was kind of struggling with what to do with it
and
I want it to
you know if I'm gonna do it
I want to do it properly
and for it to make a difference
but initially it was just so I could put out scarabs
to be honest
just a bit like Snake Pit
I guess like it's
I beat him
I got to seven releases
yeah
I mean
no surprise there
he's a fucking robot
he's a machine
so you've got to put a seven out now
and trump him by one
yeah
exactly
but I mean I started
you know
like
I sort of started Snake Pit
because I sort of felt
if I'm on it
it's probably a bit of pressure that
oh you should have a label
like you should have a label by now
that's interesting
like what kind of pressure
just because other people do it
not that anyone would say
but just looking around
and seeing other people
and going oh shit
okay
what's next for me
like
you know
logically
it would be to have a label
yeah
and then
and then yeah
and the name came around
there's Piranha Paul
and I'm looking at things
and I was like
Piranha Paul
I'll be Snake Pit
so it's like
that's what they look
they're quite linked
yeah
but that was just the catalyst
and yeah
again like Ben said
I should
I need to really start
my thing up
and sort of
but it was just a place
to put stuff out
that I liked
like the last release
I did was a hip hop release
was a hip hop tune
I did with my mate Stapleton
that we'd had
we'd been sitting on for six years
and I was like
it's my label
I'll do what I want
I don't care if you buy it
or you don't buy it
it's
I want it out there in the world
and it's there
you know so
I think it's also an expectation thing
as well
I was struggling with
you know
like
Ed Rush putting out
starting his own label
it's like
yeah
people would expect it to be a certain way
and like I said before
it's
if you want to do it
really properly
it's a big commitment
and it's like
you need
like a good team around you
and you need like the resources
and stuff
and when you're like
trying to make tunes
DJing at the weekends
picking the kids up from school
being a dad
being a husband
like there's not
in order to do it properly
you've got to really find the time
and the commitment
or find someone that's going to do it
who shares your vision
and really want to roll their sleeves up
and get involved
and do it for the long haul
because initially there's no money in it
I hear that
I mean
do you want to get involved
and help me build this thing
and then
maybe
you can get a slice of the pie
a bit down the line
when it's done well
and I think we still quite like
being the artist as well
yeah
we still like being
because I think you notice
some people
when they put that
label manager hat on
their own productions
might
well they take the back seat
yeah
do you know what I mean
and I think drum and bass
is that genre
that if you take the back seat
in production
especially the stuff that we do
the neuro stuff
if you
if you know
if you step off that train
for
for one second
it's gone down the tracks
and it takes a bit of time
to catch back up to it
we've seen it all the time again
it moves that quickly
that you can solve
you can take a year off
and then people come back
and it's like
well this is like a different world now
do you know what I mean
everything sounds different
and I think we're
quite driven in that way
that we want to be
and still feel that we have
a voice
and something to say
even though I'm
you know
we're getting older now
and you know
we're not the hot young kids
we still feel that we have a voice
and
that's important to me
so I think that's why
perhaps the label is not
at the forefront
is because I still want us
I've still got shit to say
I hear that
and I see that tension
in artists like yourself
and I was
chatting with Chris Prolix
about this
you know like
I think it's kind of amazing
the number of releases
that he's managed to get to you
with Trenkill
he's smashing it with Trenkill
yeah
yeah like it's amazing
he's going to have his 50th release this summer
wow
crazy
and he's kept his artists
sort of integrity
not integrity
but his work
ethic
yeah
and the sound
he's got great sound
the label's got a sound
yeah
which is kind of what you want
love you Chris
but that
that takes its toll
you know
that's hard to balance
yeah
being a touring artist
and family
and all these things
so
yeah
I think we
like
at Valkyrie
like we recognise
like
we want to try and help a bit
with this
like
we see how like
like crews and like teams are so important
you know to give people the space
to focus on what they do best
100%
and just as a bit of like a rally point
you know for people to come together
and I don't know
it's interesting seeing like
even like the label landscape
that I grew up with
fragmenting
and twisting
like over the years
like
like Ram was a big like active force
when I grew up
yeah
now it's not
not that same thing anymore
no
and it's like
you know
on smaller levels as well
or even with like
legacy brands
who like
they kind of transform
and they evolve too
and do
do different things
so
yeah
I guess we're
that's
that's the space that we're
we're trying to help with
and do some things
yeah no it's great
it's great
yeah
one thing I was going to ask you Gareth
was like
heard you did some like engineering
for like
Alpha Magic
back in the day
yes
like our
was that like Hard House
it was a
it was a big music distributor
so there was like
vinyl distribution
SRD
Alpha Magic
so what were you actually doing there
so
I first started
a friend of mine
Macky worked there
and he was basically
sort of doing the A&R
so sort of selling
yeah
oh yeah
I'll have a little bit more water please
yeah have a top up
thank you Tim
thanks mate
lovely
thank you
so yeah
he got me basically
so
for three days a week
I was selling
so I'd ring the record shops up
I had an area
and I'd ring the record shops up
and go hey mate
like
we've got this new
12 from this artist
blah blah blah
and if he needs
I'd play a little bit to him down the phone
and he'd be like
yeah right
give me 10 copies of that
five copies of this
whatever
primaries
and then for the rest of the week
I'd be in the studio
because they had
they owned
quite a few labels
in-house labels
they owned
Outbreak
Invaders
Cell Recordings
there was a
like a bootleg label
called Camouflage
so they're all ones
that they let
that they had in-house
that they would get artists to work on
so they had a studio downstairs
so I used to just write them tunes
so that was that was
effectively my job
was to just write
different tunes
for these different labels
under different names
different
aliases and stuff
so it was like
it was an amazing experience
to to get paid
for like a job
yeah
but learn
so much
you know because obviously I was getting
I was getting it
everything was cut to vinyl
and
you get test presses
promos
and you know
so I'd be able to hear
what I was doing
okay
shit the snare is too loud on this
okay bass
there's no bass fuck
I need to turn it up next time
and then you would learn
this this system of going okay
bass needs to be up
and then ultimately get to that point
where your mixes are like
yes
I can mix
and it sounds good on vinyl
sounds like a place
with like the right amount of pressure
where you could like stretch and grow
it was absolutely perfect
and then it got to the point
where I was like
I sort of pushed my luck a little bit
and I was like
well you do know
if I could work for my own studio
I wouldn't have to come up to like
it was near
Willsden Junction
the place
it was quite a bop for me
I was like
and then you'll get better music
because I'll be in my own studio
and then the boss was like
Jerry's name was
he used to be the tour manager
for the Sex Pistols
but he ran this company
and he was like
yeah it makes sense
go for it
so I was like
effectively just working
I had a job
but I was just going to my own studio
whenever I wanted
work for as long as I wanted
as long as I turned in like
four tunes a month
they were happy
so yeah
it was the greatest two
two three years of my life
I think really
of like just having no pressure
and learning so much
and being around
the like the
the machine that is music
you know the whole point of like
recording your stuff to a CD
or to DAT
sending it off
getting it mastered
checking the test presses
making sure the artwork's okay
the whole process of
you know how long it took
yeah it was great
the creative
but then also like
the back end
the back end of all of that
yeah like music being a product
that you have to commit to
and get out there into the world
yeah and it has to
this has to happen
and it has to sell
and it has to
you know you have to
ring the record shops
and get orders
and you know so
and then going down to the warehouse
and seeing the boys
the two Italian boys
that worked down there
who were loading all the van up
with the
and then go out on his deliveries
it was just the whole
it was the whole thing
it was this whole like ecosystem
like
I find all that fascinating
because like again like
I didn't get to engage with someone
so like
I'm watching movies like
Human Traffic
and stuff and like
peering in from the outside
yeah yeah yeah yeah
on that kind of like
music house culture
and
and all of that
yeah
and just going into a record shop
and asking for a tune
you know
and then just like
or just going in there
and going all right mate
and then
you get into the point
where they know your face
so then they're like
all right mate
and they're just
and then they're just already
sorting your tunes out
because they know what you like
they're like
oh he's a drummer bass boy
so
and then if you got to know them
even better
you'd be like
oh you can have the promos
and the test presses
that are under here
that no one gets
or the band's coming in 20 minutes
you might want to wait around
just wait around
because SRD band's coming
you're like
oh that means like
hardware
trouble on vinyl
promos
oh I'll wait
I'll wait here for another bit
yeah
you know
and
and there's like a humanity
and like a buzz about that
which is like
community
yeah
connection as well
I think that's it isn't it
it's a community
you know
and yeah
things
things might be different now
but I don't know
I think we just
we need to get creative
and find ways to just read
like really
a great community
where we can
yeah
absolutely
and I think
you know
getting collectibles back
is a great thing
you know what I mean
like the
the community thing
and actually having things
that people can collect
and buy
and invest into
not just having this sort of
invisible thing
that just exists
on their phone
like
yeah
tangible products
physical things
that
that are still a reflection
of the label
and the artist
but just in a different way
yeah because
like this
this is
this is our passion
like
you know
people would put
like vinyl records
like the sleeves up on the wall
like
yeah
they would like really get the
I still have my albums on my wall now
I have my all my albums
on the wall
because
yeah
it's what
it's the only thing I can do
I have my box of CDs
all of the
you know
all the stuff I've made
I've kept all of it
yeah
because it
it's all I have
it's
it's interesting seeing some people
like in the digital era
like trying to find some new ways
to engage with that
like
I think it's cool that people still do vinyl
yes
I guess we can talk about vinyl
I don't know when this is going to go up
but we can
yeah well I was sort of skirting around
I didn't really quite want to go
around but
we can talk about it
okay
yeah
he's super excited that we're doing vinyl
for the EP
it's
and like I said to you
when we were talking before
that was another
reason that we wanted to go with you guys
as well as the community
as well as we get on with you
and we were friends
is that you want
you were keen on pushing that
and it's something that
we come from
and we miss
and
it's
it's like another way of kind of
showing your story
yeah
you know
it's how the artwork looks
and
what little things you can put
that
you know
that sort of explain
different dimensions
for you
for you to be creative
there you go
be artists
exactly
yeah
because you can switch up the artwork
on different releases
yeah
or maybe do
an extra track on one
or whatever it might be
or do something a bit wild
with the shape of the vinyl
yeah
possibly
I'll probably get in trouble
if I say any more
yeah
just know it's going to be
so sick
and you need one
yeah
and there probably won't be any more
when we've done it
so
no one run
that's it
exactly
golden run
yeah
let's talk about something different
so like related to it
it's a killer of killers
like the EP
so like
I know you guys
like both
like you love movies
love like sci-fi
yeah
like that
that kind of run
like that's a deep source of inspiration
oh I do
see the big grin on my face
yeah
so what we'll start off
alien or predator
you have to pick one
predator
I'll probably go alien
probably go alien
yeah
just
just because of the impact
it had on me
when I was a kid
that
that scene of seeing that
alien come out of that stomach
was just like
I've never seen anything like it before
and it just kind of
it's going to stay with me forever
and also I'm obsessed with aliens
so there's another thing
tell us a bit more about that
well I just
I don't know
I just think that the whole
as we progressing with technology
and
Elon Musk is doing his thing
I think the whole
all these possibilities are opening now
you know life on Mars and all that
I think
there's
I'm hoping in my lifetime
we see something that
we think all might be possible that
there's more than just us
I think we're getting closer
and closer and closer to that
so yeah
I just
I kind of love that whole ideology
it's a big topic isn't it
like are we alone
in the universe
like it's one of those things
like it would just transform everything
yeah
especially if they came down
and just blew us all up
we were right
yeah
we're like Independence Day moment
the flying saucers come down
I mean it would like instantly
kind of
people wouldn't
it would diminish like racism
and stuff all of a sudden
it's all
hold on a minute
I'm not worried about
yeah
another race anymore
I'm worried about another species
like what the hell's going on
there's a prototypes track
called Species
where they have this vocal sample
and it's like
it was like the one thing that brought us together
as a species
like about like an alien invasion
I love that sample
same
I love that shit
yeah
it's great
okay so alien
alien this side
predator on this side
haven't you got some Xenomorph stuff in your studio
I've got lots
yeah
I love it both
but if you had to ask me to choose
that will be my choice
but yeah
I love it from
you know
I used to
rent videos
VHS is with my dad on a Saturday
yeah
it was our little thing
and we would go to the local video shop
in a local town
and get like a couple of videos
and some snacks
and a little bottle of Coca-Cola
for the evening
and that would be my
me and my dad's thing
we would sit there and watch films
and he would never hold back
on what films I could watch
so we did like
that's where I did Total Recall
Commando
like
like all the good Arnie films
like it was just brutality
and then I just remember
always remember watching Predator
and it just like
blow in my mind
and it's just
and I don't know whether it's the
it's the
the connection with my dad
that
that makes it so long lasting in me
but I have it tattooed on me
multiple places
I've written multiple tunes
about
many of the films
you know
the EP name
is directly
influenced by
one of the films that came out
so
yeah I just love it
I love films
I love where it takes me and
It's a special kind of creative world
isn't it
yeah I had a similar experience
like with my dad growing up
like
I'm old enough to remember going
and like looking at the videos in Tesco
yeah
like
you know
just going out and get some groceries
and like
like what videos have come in
yeah
you know watch
watch those same kind of films
it's just
there's something about that
that
that weird space
like
sci-fi like
you can recognize parts of the world
but then this
they're transformed
and they're kind of
yeah
yeah I just
I just love it
maybe a bit of the shock and awe as well
that like we get in D&B like
they
they're shocking
they're provoking
yeah
they're very
they're very connected
the sort of
those you know
and I'd watch a film
and then
that would lead me to write
so I'd
write my own sort of soundtrack
yeah
to that film
in my own mind
like this is
if I was doing a trailer music
this would be it
and I'd
and then at the end of it
I'd have a
six-minute drum and bass tune
but it would have all the things that
you know
I sort of felt influenced
by watching the film
yeah
whilst we're on this topic
I don't know if I've ever told you this
maybe I have
but
my
my dad
some
he doesn't listen to drum and bass
he's in his 60s
yeah
somehow
I don't know how this happened
he stumbled
across Marauder
nice
on like on Spotify
or something
yeah
that's the one
one DB tune that you listen to
that hits his reference point
that's his reference point
he would like
like I've not prompted this
it's not as good as Marauder
I bet he compares everything to it
but like that's
that's the one tune
and he'd like listen to it on his commute
into London on the train
amazing
yeah
so
that's cool
well every now and then
when I
as I like
tell him what I'm doing on my journey
through the DMV world
they're like
I'll be talking to the spaceship guy this week
like
because there's that song
point it like
yeah, yeah, yeah
I'll take command of the spaceship
yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah
so I wanted to share that
I thought you might find that funny
that's wicked
tell him
thank you very much
and hello from me
yeah
we can't talk about
DMV and movies
about talking about Blade Runner
either
I mean that's like
not just the content of the film
but this is the soundtrack
as well
the Vangelis strings
yeah
every time a spaceship comes in
it would be like a reese
like reese noises
I'm like
wow
this is the one
trying to sample
all these little snippets out of it
just amazing
so inspirational
one of the films
where you sit and watch it
and I just want to make a tune
yeah
like not not just the
the art of it
and like the future world
they're created
but like the sound to match with it
it feels like it was so ahead of its time
yeah
and I think it was a big influence
on people like Dillinger as well
a lot of his strings
from like
this is a threshold
and
Silver Blade
and all that
they're very
Vangelis
definitely
influenced aren't they
yeah
like I see it in so many ways
like the like the long tail of that film
like the synth use
like I know
that Subfocus like used
like an emulator of that
for the Solar System
intro
yeah
like
it's just touched so many
drum and bass tunes
in the past
yeah tell us a bit more about like
the sort of sci-fi links
with like the early days
virus
and like
and wormhole
and all of that
Matt's
a big sci-fi guy as well
yeah
similar
love for Blade Runner
that was
our main inspiration
probably back then
just the
like we said
the soundscape and stuff
also the Ian Banks books
he did like
four or five different books
one was called
Player of Games
okay
yeah
and it's just talking about
a future world
and this ideology
and kind of mixing
kind of robots
with humans
and that whole kind of thing
and
those books are also
inspiring
for just getting ideas
and thinking outside the box
and experimenting
with sound and stuff
and pushing things
kind of in a different direction
I guess a lot of this
maybe was happening
like across the backdrop
do you remember like the Y2K thing
like
as we were approaching the
like the year 2000
oh yeah
everything's gonna shut down
yeah
the world's gonna end
or like
2000 just felt like
this big massive thing
and like we're kind of moving
it was like
the future is here now
it's here isn't it
it's here
yeah
yeah it was a
it was an interesting time
like
yeah definitely
from
in my childhood
like seeing that stuff
like watching The Matrix
and
all those kind of things
yeah
yeah that's another one
Matrix
yeah
oh my god yeah
so
so many times
absolutely
we've literally
yeah
all those films have been sampled
I think even there's a
there might be a little reference to it
on one of the EP tracks
there might be
there might be yeah
yeah
not saying anything
tell us a little bit more about like
so sample selection
like when
when you're working on tunes like that
yeah
do you
do you just have like massive
banks of stuff
that you've accumulated over the years
that you can draw from
or
so do you guys
go hunting for things
yeah a bit of both
yeah a bit of both like
sometimes you'll get a track name first
like an idea for a track name
and then everything will be based around that
and you'll type it into YouTube
or whatever it might be
and try and find some samples that way
or sometimes you're rolling through your hard drive
and you'll hear a vocal sample
and be like
ah
there's a tune
and you hear it in a different way
that you might not have heard before
and that can be the inspiration
so
so it can be a building block
or it can slot in
yeah
it can be the last piece
or it can be the first piece
exactly
do you know what I mean
it can be the
the catalyst of what you're making
or it can be that
that little bit of cherry on top
that you've been waiting for
you're like
and then it's like
putting the last piece of a jigsaw puzzle
where it's like click
there it is
yeah
I mean
when we decided on the name
Killer of Killers
it pretty much
pushed the whole EP in a certain direction
there's gonna be no
minimal rollers on there
no
no liquid tunes on there
no liquid
not this time guys
sorry
vocals
the only liquid is blood
as like someone said in our community
your blood dripping off the vinyl
so then every project you're in
that you're in a certain frame of mind
and you're looking for certain samples
to fit that idea
and that
that sound palette
yeah
yeah and then
and that one you sent
the one we're talking about
the reference track is you know
it had that
it had a sample from
the original film
where it came from
and it just
it was
it
what it was saying was great
and it was cool
but it just wasn't quite
sonically
cutting where it needed to cut
and be sort of as powerful
and as present as what we wanted
so then that
and that's the benefit of
technology
yeah
you can just
I can put the text in
I can break it down to text
put it into an AI genre
and it just gets spoken
and I can pick
all these different voices that I want
and I'm like
oh actually
I'll have a lady to do it this time
and then you can just
you can completely
you can start at this point
and end up over here
but with the same source material
do you know what I mean?
yeah yeah
and it just gives it a different feel
and you know
yeah
but using that sample
originally definitely pushed the track
in a certain direction
yeah
because it was like part of the
quite early on
found that sample on my hard driving
it's like this is great
this is like giving me lots of ideas and
the without you sample
yeah yeah
yeah
and I'd never heard that sample before
you get all the other stuff in Matrix sample before
all like the classic lines
yeah
not that one
but not that one
at the end
when he does a little fine call at the end
you don't
I've never heard of that in a tune
obviously heard it
but never thought about
and I don't know why
I'd never thought about putting it
because I'm usually quiet
on that sort of stuff
yeah
trying to
because if you see a little
an untapped source
you're like
oh
yeah
I'll chop that for later
because it'll be
so you found this like sampling vein
from this super mined out
yeah
so it's still there
oh my god
it was exactly
yeah we found like a little vein
in between the toes
we were like
can't wait to get in there
yeah basically
but yeah
and then like I said
with AI technology
you can just flip it
and you know
if it's not the best quality
you know I think I did it
I did it
I did it the other day
actually with a film
I just
I ran the snippet of a film
through a stem splitter
and just got the vocal
completely
you know on its own
and yeah
it was just
yeah it's great
without going too much
down the AI rabbit hole
I mean like
it's
it's kind of the hot topic
that like all musicians
are talking about
and I've seen you talk about it
before Gareth
respect to like
where the chaos lies
and like
that being almost like
your vehicle to tease out
how you feel about it
and like
your ethics
that was the impending doom
of what's coming
yeah not necessarily
the specifics of like
what it means to
music production
I think that
that whole album
was more like
being scared of like
what the fuck
is Arnold Schwarzenegger
going to walk through the door
in a minute as a Terminator
and you know
like
that's what it felt like
that was the fear
as a
as a man that's getting on
in years
in this world
and like
I'm not like
necessarily with everything
yeah
and then seeing it
everywhere
it was just like
it's quite unsettling
have you guys
heard what Diplo said
the other day
about how he's not
going to lead
top liners anymore
yeah I listened
to that interview
I listened to that
whole interview
yeah I found it
quite interesting
what did you guys
make of that
well the fact that
he'll use it
and just
and then
and he'll just
put an idea in
I think what he
actually said was
because he
he grew up reading
record notes
on the backs of records
he could
he could say
okay I want
I want a
a dance hall
via bass line
but in the style of
blah blah blah
and give a specific
dance hall
bass players name
to the AI
and to get stuff out
but then
and he said that
that would
sometimes actually
just go and be
the track
what's
he'll split the stems
from AI
and then someone
drums and that's
someone who's so
meticulous and who's
like being through
that grafting process
but both of you
you know to
own your stripes
how does that
make you feel
thinking about
people shipping
music product
in that kind of
impersonal detached
way how does that
make you feel
feels like the end
doesn't feel like
a good
it doesn't feel like
the way we should
be going music is
I get utilizing
and making the
most out of
the tools that
are there
for instance
with an AI
voice to make it
clear and sonically
punch better in
the track
but still convey
the message that
the vocal had
yeah that's
I think is acceptable
of doing it
but to get AI
to prompt it
to say I want a
hard neuro track
on this style of
ed russian optical
with you know
a middle breakdown
like the rogue
it's just
nah that's not
for me
it does feel like
it's just
the ultimate cheat
code and it's
not it's removing
I mean it
really gets
I mean it's getting
there isn't it
I wouldn't say
it's perfect
yet
but
if you
if you can
code human
emotion
like sadness
and happiness
if you can
write that
into code
and bundle that
into AI
and ask it to
and it can
spit it out
perfectly
then I guess
we're all
fucked
because
then the
creativity of
the human
will be
able to
write about
their experiences
in life
which AI
will never
have
like going
through a
breakup
or losing
someone
or stuff
like that
will evoke
real
emotive
thoughts
and feelings
and create
you
and push
you to be
creative
in a certain
way
which AI
won't be
will be
something that
they won't be
able to
replicate
but I think
it can be
useful as a
tool
for ideas
maybe if you
get stuck
with something
like I've
got this
drop here
and I don't know
what to do
for the
roll out
section
or I've
got this
or that
or you know
maybe
asking it
to come up
with a
it's too
dystopian
it's not
an ideal
situation
kind of lacking
humanity
well we've cheated
ourselves out of
something that's
joyous
and beautiful
we would have
in our
endless
pursuit
on making
things quicker
and easier
we would have
cheated
ourselves out of
one of the
most beautiful
things that
a human
can do
which is
write a
tool
for music
and you know
I think it's a
very slippery
slope down
AI
it's interesting
seeing people
talking about it
and I guess
everyone is
on a journey
trying to
figure out
their own
ethics
values
and then
different
communities
have different
strong
stances
some like
very pro
some very
anti
you know
we've got used to
other things
coming in
in our lives
smartphones etc
we didn't have
them when we
were born
but we've
utilised
them in our
lives but
I just think
there's limits
to what AI
should be able
to do
yeah I agree
I think limitation
is the key
I think it's
cool for them
to be able
to do the
mundane
jobs that
literally anyone
can do
exactly
I think doing
stuff like that
freeing us up
as a race
in order to
explore our
own creativity
a bit more
and do things
that we enjoy
doing that
brings us joy
and makes us
happy
I think that's
gonna be
excellent
but the second
it's replacing
us creatively
and it's
kind of
emulating
stuff that
we can only
have only
done as
humans
I think
we're
in trouble
you know what I'm
really curious
about
I grew up
in this
transition
time
between
social media
coming in
so I'm
quite like
an analog
childhood
I read
a lot
watched
videos
whatever
and then
social media
has come
in
and now
AI
what I'm
doing
is
I feel
very grateful
to have
had like
to almost
be able
to train up
a rich
imagination
it's a
really useful
thing that I
have in life
I'm very
grateful for
it could be
limiting isn't it
I wonder how
things might
be different
you just type
a prompt
into AI
it's like
outsourcing
imagination
that's what
using your imagination
as a child
is challenging
it's like you create
these worlds
you have games
with your friends
and I think
once we start
getting to that
point
we're trying to
eliminate that
like again
it's just
I think it boils down
to purpose
as well
like what's your
I think every human
like we need
purpose in
order to feel
like we have
value
in order to stay
sane and in
order to get
out of bed
let's hope
it doesn't come to that
we've got two
minutes left
so before we go
for those who
haven't listened to
the EP yet
so tell people
a little bit
about it
why should they
listen to it
what can they
expect
it's banging
yeah
it's pretty
hardcore
if you like
hard aggressive
drum and bass
with some
really nice
sonic textures
that's been
put together
with love
and care
odd years
of experience
go and
check it out
because you
won't be
disappointed
and being
stress tested
yes
it's working
really really
well in the
clubs
highlights of
some of the
sets at the
moment and
some of the
feedback
from the
two tracks
that have
already seen
the light of
day
have been
incredible
very encouraging
I hope
your little baby
out into the
world
hope it's
going to be
well received
and do well
because we're
really proud
of it
and I think
it's beautiful
in its own
dark
twisted way
yeah
you always
get a bit
anxious
when you're
about to
sort of
because it is
like
it's a
part of
yourself
your little baby
like
cover
the vinyl
yeah
no more
gatekeeping
no we're
very excited
to see
what people
make of it
and we hope
yeah we
hope they
enjoy it as much
as we enjoyed
making it
because we
really did
enjoy making
this
and all the
Valkyrie side
we're
incredibly
excited
and like
very
very thankful
to be on
board as well
yeah we're
excited to see
what you know
what we can do
so
yeah
well that's
this is
going to be
literally the
first release
for us
hopefully the
first of
many
yes
and we
literally could
not think
of a
better way
to get
things off
so yeah
thank you
like we
said it's
the killbox guys
to Gareth
and Ben
if you haven't
checked out
killer of
killers yet
then please
go and do
that
you can find
it on bandcamp
on beatport
and all good
streaming
services
we'll be
back again
soon
for
episode 2
with another
label artist
in the
meantime
please do
check out our
socials
channel
and we'll
see you
next one